You might be already using a floater health
insurance for your family. You must have opted
for that, because buying floater health insurance
for the whole family is cheaper than buying
separate health insurance policy for each
family member. Can you do the same for your
Car and bike? Is it possible to buy a floater
insurance policy for your car and bike together
and save on insurance premium? Yes. You can
do this with motor floater policy which is
introduced now in India. In this video, I
will explain how to reduce your car insurance
costs every year using the motor floater policy.
Welcome to Save and Invest Smartly!
The floater motor insurance plan is a part
of the sandbox initiative, where insurers
can experiment and test innovative financial
products. The sandbox approach gives an opportunity
to experiment and learn about new technology
and product, before it’s finally adopted
and offered to larger set of people. The insurance
companies that has rolled out motor floater
policy are ICICI Lombard General Insurance
and Reliance General Insurance
What is motor floater policy?
It is a single insurance policy that covers
all the vehicles owned by a person, together.
All private vehicles, cars or two-wheelers
registered under a single owner can be covered
under this policy.
Maximum of up to 5 vehicles can be covered
under the same policy.
How is the Sum Insured calculated?
Every vehicle has an IDV - Insured Declared
Value, fixed by the insurer based on the brand,
model and age of the vehicle. It may be approximately
equivalent to the market value of the vehicle.
For example, let us consider you own a car,
a bike and a scooter all registered under
your name. If the IDV value for each of these,
arrived based on market value are let's say, Car - 500000
Bike - 35000,  Scooter - 15000
In case of motor floater policy, IDV of
each vehicle is calculated separately and
the one with highest IDV is the primary vehicle
and other vehicles are considered secondary
vehicles. In our case,
the car becomes the Primary Vehicle
and the Bike and Scooter become the  Secondary Vehicles
The Sum Insured is the IDV of the primary
vehicle.
Therefore the Sum Insured in our case
is 500000
The Sub limit of each insured vehicle depends
on individual IDV
For example, if the bike is lost and you
apply for claim under the floater policy,
then the maximum claim is limited to 35000
as per its IDV.
With every claim, the sum insured of the
policy also reduces.
For example, if you have claimed 35000 for
your bike when it is lost, the updated sum
insured will be (500000-35000)=465000 .
The Sum Insured will be reset to maximum value
automatically during the next year policy renewal.
But in case, you want to reset the sum insured
mid year, then you may do it by paying an
additional amount.
What are the Coverage Options available?
You may choose any of the 2 coverage options that are available
Option 1: Stand Alone Own Damage Cover
Own Damage Insuranceis a customized motorinsurancepolicy
designed to protect you and your insured vehicle
from yourown damages. That is, this policy
covers against any loss or damage to your
vehicle or its accessories due to:
Fire, explosion, self-ignition, accidental
damage
or during Transit, that is when the vehicle is shifted
from one place to another
Natural disasters like earthquake, flood,
cyclone, etc.
or Burglary, theft, riot, etc.,
Option 2: Own Damage with Third Party
This option covers everything in Option 1
plus the third party coverage.
Third party policycovers theinsuredagainst
any legal liability arising out towards third
parties due to accidental injury or death
of a person and any damage caused to third
party property.
Let's see the advantages of motor floater
policy:
You can buy one single floater motor insurance
plan that covers all vehicles that you own.
Some of you may have 2 cars or some of you
may have a car and a bike, or some people
may have 2 or 3 bikes in their family. All
these could be covered using a single floater
motor insurance policy. This will save a lot
of time as the insurance buying or renewal
process would be only once a year for all
vehicles together.
You don't have to fill up several proposal
forms and submit proofs for each vehicle separately.
A single documentation is sufficient for all
the vehicles together.
There is no hassle of remembering multiple
renewal dates. Just remember one date for
renewing the policy in a year for all vehicles
together.
If you have to update some details in
your policies like change of address, etc.,
you may do it in a single go for all vehicles
together.
The premium paid for a floater policy
covering all vehicles together is lesser than
the total premium paid, if separate policies
are bought for each vehicle. You may save
up to 20% on your premium if you go for motor
floater policy.
You can add or delete vehicles later easily
to the same policy, whenever you buy a new
vehicle or sell one of the existing vehicle.
All other regular motor insurance benefits
like no claim bonus, cancellation, etc are
also available on the motor floater policy.
How to apply for motor floater policy?
If you want to get the insurance from ICICI
Lombard General Insurance,
visit www.icicilombard.com. You will see
various menu options.
Click on Products and then select the
option "Single Owner Multiple Vehicle".
You will get a form to fill up your name,
mobile number and email id. Fill up the details
and tick the check box to agree the terms
and conditions. Click on Proceed.
This will take you to the next page to
fill up the number of vehicles. From the first
drop down, select the number cars you own
and from the next drop down, select the number
of two wheelers that you own. Click on 'Submit'.
The insurance agent will contact you to
get further details from you and proceed with
the documentation.
To apply the motor floater policy from Reliance
General Insurance,
visit www.reliancegeneral.co.in. You will
see various menu options.
Click on the menu 'Car' and then select
the option 'Motor Floater Insurance'.
You will get a form to fill up your name
and contact details. Fill up the form, tick the
check box and click on 'Submit'.
The insurance agent will contact you to
get further details from you and proceed with
the documentation.
The floater policy will definitely save time
and money for you in the long run. Give it
a try when you apply or renew your car insurance
or bike insurance next time. Let me know your
thoughts on this new policy type in the comments
section. Also, write down if you have more
queries on this.
Hope this video was helpful to you! Subscribe
and hit the bell icon to watch more such videos.
Give a thumbs up if you like the video. Thank
you!